MIR NAZEER AHMED TALPUR

Consultant of DRR & Monitoring, Evaluation

HOUSE NO: 30 Jugnu Town, Mirpurkhas Sindh, Pakistan Mob 03333619101&03153619101 Email -ceofdc@gmail.com

PROFILE

Result-Based-Management (RBM) oriented, intellectually sound program management/M&E professional coming from a multi-lateral development occupation to offer M&E /management services. Highly motivated to leverage over Eleven (11) years of achievements (more than 4 years in program management and more than 6 years in monitoring and evaluation), during a qualitatively diverse career in multicultural settings in the realm of development sector to render dedicated services for both efficient and effective delivery of M&E / management programs. Qualification includes M. Sc (H) Geography; comprehensive field and in-house trainings; extensive experience in areas highlighted in the subsequent box:

Specialties' keywords summary: Program / Project Evaluation, DRR Specialist, Program / Social Audits, Organizational Assessment, Project Design, , Budgeting, Social Mobilization, Emergency Humanitarian Assistance, Social Mobilization, Report Writing, Team leading, Capacity Building, Training of Trainers, Development Planning, Event Organizer (Conferences, Seminars, Campaigns), Public Speaking, Office Administration & HR

EXPERIENCE SUMMARY

Job Title	Organization	# of Projects/ Assignments	Time spent
Chief Executive Officer	FDC Friend Development Consultant	13 Assignment	August 2012 to today
DRM Coordinator	UNDP/ NDMA	DRR Assignment	September 2010 to August 2011
DRR Consultancy	LHDP Badin / Plan International, Pakistan	Prepared UC and Village Level Contingency Plan	2011-12
Consultant	SSEWA Pak MirpurKhas	06 Projects ongoing	Presently working
Consultant	PVDP Mirpurkhas	All projects ongoing	Presently working
Programme Manager Monitoring, Evaluation & Research, Sindh Region	DevCon Development Consultants (pvt.) Limited Rawalpindi	Several Assignments	August 2011 to December 2012
Consultant - Monitoring & Evaluation	DevCon Development Consultants (pvt.) Limited Rawalpindi	12 assignments	1 and a half years-
Provincial Data Collection Coordinator	ASIAN DEVELOPMENT BANK (ADB)	01 project	2 months
Assistant Monitoring & Evaluation Office	Sindh Agricultural Forestry Workers Coordinating Organization (SAFWCO)	Several projects	2 and a half years
District Coordinator- Mirpurkhas	Sindh Agricultural Forestry Workers Coordinating Organization (SAFWCO)	02 project	2 years
Program Officer	Sindh Agricultural Forestry Workers Coordinating Organization (SAFWCO)	Several	2 years
Freelance Writer, Surveyor and Evaluator	Different Organization	26 Assignment	During the Job

DETAILED CHRONOLOGICAL ACCOUNT OF SERVICES RENDERED AND LEARNING PROFILE

DRR Consultancy:

- Prepare Union council "Community Based Disaster Risk Management" (CBDRM) Plan for 3 Union council of District Badin, Pakistan), for Plan Internation, Pakistan.
- Translate 8 District Disaster Contingency plans for NDMA / UNDP.
- Prepare District Rain Flood Contingency plan for District Badin 2011.
- Prepare School Safety Plans and Health Facility Safety Plans for IP LHDP Badin and Founded by Plan International

Prepare 54 Village Disaster Management Committees and plans in District Badin.

UNDP/NDMA

District DRM Coordinator.

[September 2010 - August 2011]

Key responsibilities

- Work closely with the DCO office to make the DDMA functional, and facilitate coordination with various departments and stakeholders.
- Support the DCO office in developing gender sensitized annual work plan and budget for the DDMA.
- Provide support to the DCO office for development and preparation of PC-1 for budget allocations to DDMA. Ensure that PC-1s in preparation are sensitized with DRM components and gender considerations.
- Facilitate the establishment of DDMAs office along with the appointment of some designated staff.
- Manage the district level trainings for government authorities and communities' men and women on DRM.
- Facilitate in carrying out rapid needs and early recovery assessments; organize drills, awareness raising and other planned activities under the One UN DRM programme.
- Liaison with respective PDMA or other district/provincial/ federal departments as per requirement.
- Submit project reports to NDMA/UNDP as per the schedule and ensure that progress and achievements are highlighted against the outcomes and outputs of the approved project document.

Mointoring & Evaluation Consultant

SSEWA Pak Mirpur Khas (Presently Working)

Task Dimensions:

- 06 projects are being monitored & eveluated of the organization as per supported donors requirements.
- Assigned project's soft and hard components are being monitored and evaluated as per IP

Mointoring & Evaluation Consultant

PVDP Mirpur Khas (Presently Working)

Task Dimensions:

- All projects are being monitored & eveluated of the organization as per supported donors requirements.
- Assigned project's soft and hard components are being monitored and evaluated as per IP

Provincial Programme Officer Monitoring Evaluation & Research (Sindh Region)

November 2011 to date (Presently Working) DevCon Development Consultants (pvt.) Limited, Rawalpindi Task Dimensions:

- End of the Project Evaluation of Early Recovery Project for Flood Affected Communities of District Jamshoro Implemented by PAKISTAN FISHERFOLK FORUM PFF and founded by TroCaire
- Reviewed and finalized End Project Evaluation Study Report of World Vision Pakistan Flood Response Program: Integrated WASH and Early Recovery Assistance for Flood Affected Communities in KPK & Punjab
- Reviewed and Finalized Mid Term Evaluation Report of unicef / Plan Pakistan Up-scaling and Early Recovery Program on Rural Sanitation in 3 flood affected districts, Jaccobabad, Jaferabad, and Thatta

Provincial Data Collection Coordinator, Sindh ASIAN DEVELOPMENT BANK. (ADB)

Sep 2011 to Oct 2011

Task Dimensions:

➤ Desk Review Stage: Gathered information through a Desk Review of existing information available from federal and Provincial government, other international sources (UN agencies, NDMA, PDMA, National & international NGO, etc).

- ➤ Field Visit stage: Visit partner agencies both Government and non-government and collect information from public (primarily, district and lower-tier authorities, and private sector bodies (primarily, RSPs, NGOs, medical & relief teams, etc), and internation agencies mobilized in the affected area.
- ➤ Coordinate and cross check the gathered data with GOP & UN agencies such as UNICEF, WFP, UNDAC, UN Disaster Management Unit, etc, for necessary revalidation of the collected data, and any improvements/data cleaning required thereof.
- > Develop a sector specific data base focusing on social and dender impacts including affected vulnerable groups.
- > Coordinate and support social and gende consultants and the DNA teams on the above mentioned tasks.

Consuntant-Monitoring and Evaluation

DevCon Development Consultants (pvt.) Limited, Rawalpindi

- Tracer Study of Kindernothilfe (KNH) Germany supported 5 hostelsin Sialkot, Narowal, Hyderabad, Sanghar (Team Leader): under Residential Child Care Program for Social, Semi and Full Orphans, the study looked into the current systems, records and satisfaction level of both the residing students and the former home children to cover the benefit angle (impact) the quality of services provided to them by these hostels; seen if the enrolled children meet the required criteria as set by the hostel management and KNH. Highlighted strengths of the program; outlined areas of improvements and gave strategic recommendations to fill in gaps with an aim to include in the future programming.
- ➤ Program Evaluation of Pakistan Poverty Alleviation Fund (PPAF) supported SAFWCO Sindh Agricultural and Forestry Workers' Coordinating Organization's Social Mobilization Program(Team Leader) Evaluation team based their evaluation methodology on the 6 main guiding principles/outcomes of PPAF social mobilization program and assessed the professional capacities and skills of social mobilization staff, identified opportunities to build their capacities keeping in view the right based dimensions of social mobilization in PPAF and Safwco context (Completed the assignment as per agreement within stipulated timeframe and agreed outputs).
- Program Evaluation of "Creating Community Model for Sustainable Development program (CMSD) funded by Oxfam-Novib toSindh Agricultural and Forestry Workers' Coordinating Organization(Team Leader):undertook a systematic and impartial examination of CMSD project against set objectives while keeping in view the findings of mid term review with the intention to draw lessons to improve program strategy, effectiveness, processess, practices and indentified new directions, areas to be considered for planning future projects of similar nature (Completed assignment as per agreement within stipulated timeframe n agreed outputs).
- ➤ Program Evaluation(Co led) of SSEWA-Pak's Child Focused Integrated Community Development Program supported by KNH in 25 villages in Mirpurkhas district, Sindh. The overall objective of the evaluation was to assess the degree to which the project met its objectives as outlined in the project proposal and to extract key lessons /recommendations to enhance the impact of future programming by SSEWA-Pak
- Social / Program Audit of multiple Emergency Relief projects of SSEWA-Pak during recent flood, supported by UNHCR, Tearfund, KNH and ICCO
- ➤ Quality Inspection of Agricultural Inputs at various stages (grading, processing, treatment, shipment) for the early recovery of flood affectees in Swat, & Deer
- > Base Line Surveyof Food Security Program three partner organization of ActionAid Funded by European Commission.
- Monitoring & Evaluation of the six projects & whole activities of SEWA-Pak Organization Mirpurkhas.

(2002 to

- ➤ Project Coordinator -Disaster Management Emergency Response (DMER)-Mirpurkhas 17th October 2006 to 30th April 2008, implementing SAFWCO funded by UNICEF
- ➤ District Coordinator Education -Mirpurkhas, 1st May, 2004 to 16th October 2006implementing SAFWCO funded by UNICEF
- ➤ Project Officer Arsenic Mitigation project, implementing SAFWCO funded by UNICEF
- ➤ Program Officer- Monitoring, Evaluation Research & Training Hyderabad SAFWCO
- Program Officer Dist: Sanghar in WES project implementing SAFWCO funded by Unicef
- > Social Organizer-Social Development Sector (SDS)- Sinhjoro, Shahdadpur SAFWCO

TRAININGS & CONFERENCES

Training / Workshops/ Seminars	Organized by		
Master Trainer of Water Environment & Sanitation (WES)	Unicef		
Three days training on S M C's (RGDP) project	SEF/ Unicef		
Three days training on organizational development program (ODP-III)	NOVIB/SAFWCO		
Two days training on PRA at HANDS Office Hyderabad	HANDS/ESRA		
Effective Communication Skills	SAFWCO/ PPAF		
Five days training program on Social Research	NGORC		
Two days Orientation Workshop to understand World Trade Organization (WTO) at Hotel City Gate Hyderabad	Action Aid Pakistan		
Four days training program on Art of Social Organization (ASO)	SAFWCO/PPAF		
District Level workshops on Education Districts Mirpurkhas	SEF		
Three days training program on Monitoring & Evaluation	NGORC		
Master Trainer of Social Research			
Master Trainer of Monitoring and Evaluation			

EDUCATION

M. Sc: (H) Geography 2002, University of Sindh, Jamshoro, Pakistan

DIT Skills

PERSONAL INFO

Father's Name Mir Maqbool Ahmed Talpur Date of Birth 11th July 1979

LANGUAGES

• English Urdu Sindhi & Siraiki: General Professional Proficiency